<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://help.getsol.us/blog</id>
    <title>Solus Help Center Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-01-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://help.getsol.us/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Solus Help Center Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://help.getsol.us/img/support-icon-2.svg</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[eopkg is dead, long live eopkg]]></title>
        <id>https://help.getsol.us/blog/eopkg-is-dead-long-live-eopkg</id>
        <link href="https://help.getsol.us/blog/eopkg-is-dead-long-live-eopkg"/>
        <updated>2024-01-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to the Solus Development Log.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Close watchers of our <a href="https://github.com/getsolus/packages" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">packages repository</a> may have noticed some strange looking items:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/getsolus/packages/pull/1305" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Initial inclusion of eopkg4-bin</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/getsolus/packages/issues/1316" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Testing the eopkg4-bin package</a> Warning: Minions GIF</li>
</ul>
<p>It's a long story.</p>
<p>Our package manager <code>eopkg</code> is written in Python2. Python2 was originally planned to hit end-of-life all the way back in 2015! So Solus contributors past and present have wrestled with three thorny issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do we really want to just port <code>eopkg</code> to python3? Surely we could build something newer and shinier.</li>
<li>How exactly do we want to port <code>eopkg</code> to Python3? (We'll call this ported version <code>eopkg3</code> for short)</li>
<li>How do make sure <code>eopkg3</code> works even if something goes wrong with the Python3 libraries on someone's machine?</li>
</ul>
<p>Here's the plan to solve this: Ikey and friends over at Serpent OS are actively building a new package manager <a href="https://github.com/serpent-os/moss" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>moss</em></a> that we are excited about. And they're building it with Solus in mind as an eventual user. This will be our fix for the first problem. In the meantime, we're taking a pragmatic approach to the last two issues so that (frankly) we can do more exciting things.</p>
<p>Sheepman, Livingsilver, and others completed a <a href="https://github.com/getsolus/eopkg/commits/python3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">direct Python3 port</a>, which we never expect our users to actually run directly like a traditional Python program. Instead, that port will be compiled into a <em>binary</em> using <a href="https://nuitka.net/doc/download.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">nuitka</a>. We're calling this compiled <code>eopkg3</code> binary <code>eopkg4-bin</code> for now. Critically, this binary will have <em>no dependencies</em> other than <code>libc</code>. If we can successfully swap <code>eopkg</code> with <code>eopkg4-bin</code> on user's machines, then we've solved the last issue: Python3 can be updated without worrying about also wrecking the package manager. Got it?</p>
<p>But what about Python2? Well, now that Evan and Joey have seen off a <a href="https://getsol.us/2024/01/08/solus-4-5-released/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">successful ISO release</a> with a <code>calamares</code> based installer, we can cross <code>os-installer</code> <a href="https://github.com/getsolus/packages/issues/270" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">off the list</a>. And <code>eopkg4-bin</code> will let us cross off a whole bunch more. The rest of that list is a story for another day.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>David Harder</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/davidjharder</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="eopkg" term="eopkg"/>
        <category label="devlog" term="devlog"/>
        <category label="moss" term="moss"/>
        <category label="solus" term="solus"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to the Solus Devlog]]></title>
        <id>https://help.getsol.us/blog/welcome-solus-devlog-v1</id>
        <link href="https://help.getsol.us/blog/welcome-solus-devlog-v1"/>
        <updated>2024-01-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to the Solus Development Log.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the Solus Development Log.</p>
<p>The Solus Development Log will be used by Solus Staff and outside contributors to hightlight wins and changes in Solus. Keep an eye on this space.</p>
<p>The Solus DevLog has been setup to facilitate improved communication with the outside world; wins, signficant changes, as well as challenges, within Solus. Solus Staff and contributors are encouraged to use this space.</p>
<p>The DevLog has been setup as a seperate entity to the <a href="https://getsol.us/blog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Solus Blog</a> to encourage more short form development content that doesn't require the same level of polish as an official blog post.</p>
<p>It is hoped that this will be used to help communicate what's going on in Solus such that our short-term and medium-term progress, goals, and ambitions are less of a black box to the outside world.</p>
<p>Additionally, we believe it will help provide context to any of our murmurings for any users who keep an eye on the <a href="https://github.com/getsolus/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">getsolus</a> GitHub organization page and the <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#solus:matrix.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Solus</a> Matrix channels.</p>
<p>Hope to see you back at this space soon with more content!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Joey Riches</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/joebonrichie</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="hello" term="hello"/>
        <category label="devlog" term="devlog"/>
        <category label="firstpost" term="firstpost"/>
        <category label="solus" term="solus"/>
    </entry>
</feed>